Guide to the New York City Department of Traffic Parking Lot Photographs and Related Publications 1949-1988 PR 451
New-York Historical Society
New York City Department of Traffic parking lot photographs and related publications
1949-1988
New-York Historical Society
New York (N.Y.). Department of Traffic.
PR 451
4 Linear feet in 4 record cartons.
Photographs of sites of projected and existing municipal parking lots and garages operated by the New York City Department of Traffic throughout the five boroughs. Some views show street parking conditions, towing and auto body shops, traffic congestion, and pedestrian safety posters. A number of photographs capture areas of the city that have since become unrecognizable through early 21st-century gentrification and building projects. The collection includes approximately ninety supplementary publications such as feasibility studies, master plans, and neighborhood redevelopment proposals for some of the locations documented by the photographs.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. For information on making arrangements to consult it, please go to www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joel Tolchinsky, 2022.
Arrangement
The collection is organized by format in two series:
Series I.
Photographs, 1958-1979
Series II.
Publications, 1949-1988
Historical note
Formed to oversee tasks originally controlled by the New York Police Department, the New York City Department of Traffic, under its first commissioner, Thomas T. Wiley (1950–1961), instituted strict parking rules, changed some streets from two-way traffic to one, and installed the first parking meters (1951). To free the city's congested streets and to generate revenue in busy shopping and business districts, the department began building municipal parking lots and garages. The first garage appeared in Flushing, Queens, in 1954, followed in the 1960s and '70s by others in Jamaica, Queens, Downtown Brooklyn, East 153rd Street in the Bronx, and Eighth Avenue at West 53rd Street in Manhattan. Today, Manhattan alone boasts some 100,000 off-street parking spaces in about 1,600 facilities, some of them managed by the Department of Transportation, which succeeded the Department of Traffic in 1977.
[For further information, see Sigurd Grava, "Parking" and "Traffic" in The Encyclopedia of New York City, 2nd edition (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2010). The Green Book: Official Directory of New York City lists city-operated parking facilities for various years.]
Scope and Contents
The New York City Department of Traffic Parking Lot Photographs and Related Publications document the sites of projected and existing municipal parking lots and garages (some during construction) maintained by that agency throughout the five boroughs. Beyond these the collection's photographs (1958-1979) show street parking conditions and traffic congestion, and in some instances capture neighborhood scenes that have been so drastically changed by 21st century building projects as to be virtually unrecognizable today. The approximately ninety publications (1949-1988) supplementing the photographs—some of which were issued by the Department of Traffic, others by related city and state agencies—include feasibility studies, master plans, and redevelopment proposals for areas like Fulton Arcade (Brooklyn), Little Italy (Manhattan), and Jamaica Center (Queens).
Annual reports.; Feasibility studies.; Photographs.; Proposals.; Prospectuses.; Renderings (drawings); Business park parking facilities.; City planning -- New York (State) -- New York.; Construction projects -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Gentrification.; Parking facilities.; Parking garages.; Parking lots.; Pedestrian traffic flow.; Shopping center parking facilities.; Traffic congestion -- New York (State) -- New York.; Traffic flow -- New York (State) -- New York.; Underground parking facilities.; Urban renewal -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Queens (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Staten Island (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; New York (N.Y.). Department of Traffic.; New York (N.Y.). Department of Transportation.
- Series I. Photographs, 1958-1979
  Scope and Contents
  Photographs of sites of projected and existing municipal parking lots and garages—some during construction and after completion—administered by the New York City Department of Traffic, as well as views of street parking conditions, towing and auto body shops, traffic congestion, and pedestrian safety posters.
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized in six subseries. Files within each subseries are listed alphabetically. Titles in [brackets] were devised by the archivist.
  Subseries I.A.
  Photographs: New York City-wide and elsewhere, 1965-1971
  Subseries I.B.
  Photographs: Bronx, 1962-1974
  Subseries I.C.
  Photographs: Brooklyn, 1962-1975
  Subseries I.D.
  Photographs: Manhattan, 1963-1972
  Subseries I.E.
  Photographs: Queens, 1958-1979
  Subseries I.F.
  Photographs: Staten Island, 1962-1963
  - Subseries I.A. Photographs: New York City-wide and elsewhere, 1965-1971
    - Equipment, Univac, [1966 July 27?] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
      Interior views of an unidentified parking garage, with closeups of car fenders and bumpers. The date on the original folder may not apply to when the photographs were taken.
    - New York City—Transit Strike, [1966 August 10?] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
      The date on the original folder may not apply to when this single photograph was taken. The 1966 New York City transit strike occurred in January.
    - [Parking Field Sites], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
      Original folder labeled "Parking Field Sites 39 St. & 2 Ave." Contains views of unidentified parking lots and structures around New York City. Images of identifiable locations have been removed and filed under their respective boroughs.
    - [Photo duplication list], [1971] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
      Original folder labeled "Duplicate Pictures of Proposed Garages." Contains no photographs, only a handwritten list of "Pictures in Files," some of which were sent "for photography" on December 9, 1971.
    - [Safety and promotional photos], [1962], 1970 July 1, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
      Photographs of Traffic Department Safety Education Program posters with such slogans as "Look Before You Cross... at the Corners, Of Course" and "Mickey Mantle Says -- Play it Safe! Cross at Corners, Not mid block." Includes an image of traffic / transit officials posed with a cartoon drawing of an anthropomorphized computer on which are the words "The Best Thing That's Happened To Parking Tickets Since Disappearing Ink." One image published in the City of New York, Department of Traffic Annual Report, 1962 (see Box 3, Folder 4).
    - Taxi[s], 1968 June 12, 18, 27 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
      Views of taxis on
      (1) Park Avenue and East 59th Street (June 12, 1968)
      (2) Seventh Avenue between West 30th and 31st Streets (June 18, 1968)
      (3) Avenue of the Americas and Central Park South (June 27, 1968)
    - Towing (Authorized), 1969 October 6, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
      Views of auto body and towing companies in
      (1) Bronx (Mott Haven; 4151 Park Avenue; 291 West 230th Street)
      (2) Brooklyn (1302 60th Street)
      (3) Manhattan (3816 Ninth Avenue; 766 Elevnth Avenue)
      (4) Queens (100th Avenue & 217th Street; 56th Street & Northern Boulevard; Jamaica?)
      (5) uncertain locations
    - [Traffic Congestion], 1965, 1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
      Contents of two folders labeled "Traffic Congestion" and "Traffic Congestion N.Y.C. 1965"; views of
      (1) Fifth Avenue at 54th and 57th Streets (undated)
      (2) Madison Avenue between East 50th and 51st Streets (undated)
      (3) Park Avenue at East 29th (May 19, 1970), East 49th (May 27, 1965), and East 50th Streets (May 27, 1965)
      (4) West 37th Street and Broadway (May 27, 1965)
      (5) Queens Plaza[?] (undated)
    - [Underground garages], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
      Contents of two folders labeled "Underground Garage" and "Underground Garage's [sic] (other cities)"; views of
      (1) Boston
      (2) Chicago
      (3) Detroit
      (4) New York City, Brooklyn (Civic Center; unidentified)
      (5) New York City, Manhattan (Madison Square Park)
      (6) San Francisco
    - [Vandalized parking meters, overviews], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
      Original folder labeled "Meters—Vandalized." Contains views of vandalized meters in
      (1) Brooklyn (Albee Square Field, Grant Avenue Field)
      (2) Manhattan (Leonard Street Field, between Lafayette & Centre Streets)
      (3) Queens (Astoria, Flushing, Steinway)
      (4) uncertain locations
    - [Vandalized parking meters, closeups], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
      Original folder labeled "Meters (Vandelized)" [sic].
  - Subseries I.B. Photographs: Bronx, 1962-1974
    - [Broadway & West 242nd Street], 1972 April 26 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
      Original folder labeled "Proposed Garage, Broadway & 242nd St." Contains views of Broadway at Manhattan College Parkway, Bronx.
    - [Bruckner Expressway], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
      Original folder labeled "Bruckner Expressway Construction." Contains views of construction of the Bruckner Expressway.
    - [East 149th Street Garage] (folder 1 of 2), 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
      Original folder labeled "Bronx Hub #2 Garage N/S 149 St bet Courtland [sic] & Morris Ave." Contains views of the block bounded by East 149th Street, Morris Avenue, East 150th Street, and Courtlandt Avenue, site of the municipal garage constructed at 315 East 149th Street, Bronx.
    - [East 149th Street Garage] (folder 2 of 2), 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
      Original folder labeled "E 149th St." Contains construction views of the East 149th Street Garage, at 315 East 149th Street and Morris Avenue, Bronx.
    - [East 153rd Street Garage], 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
      Original folder labeled "Bx Hub 3rd Ave 153rd." Contains construction views of the 153rd Street Garage, 3000 Third Avenue, Bronx.
    - [Grand Concourse], 1971 August 15, September 9 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
      Views of the Grand Concourse at East 187th and 188th Streets, Bronx.
    - [Jerome Avenue - 170th Street Field], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
      A view of the Jerome Avenue - 170th Street Field, located south of West 170th Street between Inwood and Jerome Avenues, Bronx.
    - [Jerome Avenue - 190th Street Garage], 1970 May 21 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
      Original folder labeled "Garage Jerome Ave. & 190th St." Contains views of the Jerome Avenue – 190th Street Garage, 2478 Jerome Avenue, Bronx.
    - [Jerome Avenue - Gun Hill Road], 1972 October 10, 17 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
      Original items labeled "Jerome Avenue & Gun Hill Rd. Bx." Contains views of a parking lot on the east side of Jerome Avenue between East 212th Street and East Gun Hill Road, Bronx.
    - [Kingsbridge Field], [1965], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
      Construction and completed views of Kingsbridge Field, east of Broadway between West 230th Street and Verveelen Place, Bronx. One published in the City of New York, Department of Traffic Annual Report, 1965 (see Box 3, Folder 7).
    - [Westchester Square], 1972 April 11, August 9; 1975 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
      Original folder labeled "Westchester Square Bx." Contains views of the intersection of Westchester Square and Ponton Avenue, and Halperin and Roberts Avenues, Bronx. With
      (1) "Westchester Square, Bronx, Preliminary Feasibility Analysis" (March 13, 1972).
      (2) "Westchester Square, Bronx, Proposed Site for Parking Deck with Retail" [photocopied map] (May 14, 1975).
    - [Westchester - Zerega Field], [1962] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
      Views of Westchester - Zerega Field, Westchester Avenue between Zerega Avenue and Herschall Street, Bronx. Published in the City of New York, Department of Traffic Annual Report, 1962 (see Box 3, Folder 4).
    - [West Farms Road & Tremont Avenue], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
      Views of a site near the Cross-Bronx and Sheridan Expressways.
  - Subseries I.C. Photographs: Brooklyn, 1962-1975
    - [Albee Square Field], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
      A view of Albee Square Field, Flatbush Avenue between Fleet and Willoughby Streets, Brooklyn. The Abraham & Straus (A&S) and Martin's department stores on Fulton Street are visible in the background.
    - [Atlantic - Court Garage], 1969-1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
      Original folder labeled "Atlantic & Court Garage Bklyn. Pictures." Contains construction views of the municipal garage at Atlantic Avenue and Court Street, Brooklyn.
    - [Avenue M Field], 1971 March 19 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
      Original folder labeled "Ave. M. Brooklyn Pictures / Site A-1. Corner of Ave. M & E. 17th St. looking west." Contains views of the southwest corner of East 17th Street and Chestnut Avenue, just north of Avenue M, site of the current Avenue M Field, 1624 Chestnut Avenue, Brooklyn.
    - [Bay Ridge Garage], 1971-1972, 1975 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
      Original folder labeled "Bay Ridge Pictures Maps" [sic; no maps present]. Contains construction views of the Bay Ridge Municpal Parking Garage, 8501 Fifth Avenue at 86th Street, Brooklyn.
    - [Bensonhurst No. 1 Field], [1962] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29)
      A view of Bensonhurst No. 1 Field, 1763 86th Street, Brooklyn. Published in the City of New York, Department of Traffic Annual Report, 1962 (see Box 3, Folder 4).
    - [Brooklyn-Queens Expressway], 1970 August 27 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
      Original folder labeled "Brooklyn Queens Exp. Brooklyn Hights [sic]." Contains views of the split-level Brooklyn-Queens Expressway in Brooklyn Heights.
    - [Brownsville Field], [1962] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
      A view of Brownsville Field, north of Pitkin Avenue between Amboy Street and Hopkinson Avenue (now Thomas S. Boyland Street), Brooklyn. Published in the City of New York, Department of Traffic Annual Report, 1962 (see Box 3, Folder 4).
    - [Canarsie Field], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 32)
      Views of the projected site of Canarsie Field at Rockaway Parkway and Farragut Road, Brooklyn.
    - [Cypress Hills?], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
      A view of a parking field near Crescent and Fulton Streets, Brooklyn.
    - [East New York No. 1 Field], [1962] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
      Views of East New York No. 1 Field on the north side of Atlantic Avenue between Van Sinderen Avenue and Havens Place. One published in the City of New York, Department of Traffic Annual Report, 1962 (see Box 3, Folder 4).
    - [Flatbush No. 1 Field], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 35)
      Original folder labeled "Parking Field Flatbush #1." Contains one view of the northwest corner of Bedford and Snyder Avenues, showing Flatbush No. 1 Field (now occupied by P.S. 6) and the adjacent former Flatbush Town Hall at 35 Snyder Avenue, Brooklyn.
    - [Flatbush - Nostrand A. & B. Fields], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 36)
      Perspective renderings (photocopies) of a "Combined Parking Area and Playground" at Avenue H between Flatbush and Nostrand Avenues, Brooklyn.
    - [Front - York Street Field], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 37)
      A view of Front - York Street Field, where Front and York Streets converge near the Brooklyn Bridge and the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway, currently the site of the luxury tower Olympia Dumbo, 30 Front Street.
    - [Grant Avenue Field], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 38)
      Original folder labeled "Grant Ave Field for zoning variance." Contains views of Grant Avenue Field, 581 Grant Avenue, Brooklyn.
    - [Kings Highway No. 1 Field], 1965 November 18 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 39)
      Kings Highway No. 1 Field was located on the block bounded by Kings Highway, East 14th and 15th Streets, and Avenue P. The photographs in this folder show the south side of Avenue P between East 14th and 15th Streets, and the west side of East 14th Street looking south from Avenue P towards the entrance/exit to the field, which surrounded the firehouse at 1635 East 14th Street.
    - [Kings Highway No. 2 Field], [1963] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 40)
      A view of Kings Highway No. 2 Field, located just south of Kings Highway between East 13th and 14th Streets. Published in the City of New York, Department of Traffic Annual Report, 1963 (see Box 3, Folder 5).
    - [Livingston - Bond Garage], 1971 January (Offsite-box 1, Folder 41)
      A perspective drawing (photocopy) of the Livingston - Bond Garage, on Livingston Street between Bond and Hoyt Streets, Brooklyn.
    - [Park Avenue Field], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 42)
      Park Avenue Field extended on Park Avenue beneath the elevated Brooklyn-Queens Expressway from Navy Street to Grand Avenue. This folder contains a view near the intersection of Park and Vanderbilt Avenues.
    - [Williamsburg Field], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 43)
      Views of Williamsburg Field on the block bounded by Rutledge Street, Wythe Avenue, Heyward Street, Wallabout Street, and Kent Avenue, opposite Classon Triangle, Brooklyn.
  - Subseries I.D. Photographs: Manhattan, 1963-1972
    - [Broadway & Grand Street], [1963] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 44)
      A view of conditions at the intersection of Broadway and Grand Street, Manhattan, after elimination of two-way traffic. Published in the City of New York, Department of Traffic Annual Report, 1963 (see Box 3, Folder 5).
    - [Delancey - Essex Garage], 1970-1972 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 45)
      Original folder labeled "Delancey & Essex Sts. Pictures." Contains construction views of the Delancey and Essex Municipal Parking Garage, 105-113 Essex Street and 112-120 Ludlow Street, Manhattan.
    - [East 14th Street], 1969 March 21, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 46)
      Original folder labeled "14th St. Garage (Union Square) Manhattan (Pictures)." Contains views of the south side of East 14th Street between Third and Fourth Avenues, adjoining Lüchow's restaurant at 110 East 14th Street. With renderings of the municipal parking garage proposed for the site.
    - [Eighth Avenue - West 53rd Street Garage], [circa 1966] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 47)
      Views of the Eighth Avenue Municipal Garage, between West 53rd and 54th Streets, Manhattan.
    - [Garment District], 1965 November 29, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 48)
      Original folder labeled "Garment District, 38th St., Bway." Contains views of
      (1) West 36th Street between Seventh and Eighth Avenues (November 29, 1965)
      (2) West 38th Street near Sixth Avenue and between Sixth and Seventh Avenues (November 29, 1965)
      (3) West 39th Street between Sixth Avenue and Broadway, and between Seventh and Eighth Avenues (November 29, 1965)
      (4) Contact sheets of Herald Square and Times Square (undated)
    - [Manhattan Civic Center Garage], 1971 September 29 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 49)
      Construction views of the public parking garage and plaza at New York Police Department headquarters, Avenue of the Finest at Park Row, Manhattan.
    - [Sara Delano Roosevelt Park], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 50)
      Views of parking along Sara Delano Roosevelt Park near Chrystie, Forsyth, and Hester Streets, Manhattan.
    - [Second Avenue & East 40th Street], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 51)
      Original folder labeled "2nd Avenue & 40th Street, Manhattan (7 Additional Views)." Contains views of the vicinity of Second Avenue and East 40th Street, near the Queens-Midtown Tunnel entrance/exit, and Tudor City, Manhattan.
    - [Third Avenue bus lane], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 52)
      Original folder labeled "H. Bus Lane—3rd Ave. H Transportation." Contains multiple views of a transit official posed at a bus stop on Third Avenue, Manhattan.
    - [Water Street], 1965 November 16 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
      Original folder labeled "East Side—Parking Site (Water Street)." Contains views of Water Street at Hanover Square, and the northeast corner of Wall and Pearl Streets, Manhattan.
    - [West 28th Street between Broadway & Sixth Avenue], 1965 December 3 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
      Original folder labeled "Kinney Garage (28th St. West of B'way, Man.)." Contains views of a parking garage on the north side of West 28th Street between Broadway and Sixth Avenue, Manhattan (approximately 25 West 28th Street).
    - [West 33rd Street & Eighth Avenue], [1963] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
      Original folder labeled "33rd & 8th Ave." Contains views of the vicinity of West 33rd Street and Eighth Avenue, Manhattan. Date determined from a typed description of the proposed parking facility (included) and by the presence of Pennsylvania Station in some of the photographs.
    - [West 34th Street between Broadway & Seventh Avenue], 1966 July 25 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
      Original folder labeled "Mid-block crossing at 34th St." Contains views of West 34th Street between Broadway and Seventh Avenue, Manhattan, with the crosswalk extending from 130 West 34th across to Macy's.
    - [West 35th Street between Fifth & Sixth Avenues], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
      A view of a municipal parking garage, 9 West 35th Street (north side), Manhattan.
    - [West 77th Street between Central Park West & Columbus Avenue], 1971 January 21, 22 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
      Original folder labeled "77 St CPW." Contains views of the south side of West 77th Street between Central Park West and Columbus Avenue, Manhattan. A notation on the original folder indicates that the photographs dated January 22, 1971 were taken between 1:10 and 1:35 p.m.
  - Subseries I.E. Photographs: Queens, 1958-1979
    - [Astoria Field], 1958, [1962] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
      Before and after construction views of Astoria Field on 29th Street between Astoria Boulevard and Hoyt Avenue South, Queens. Later view published in the City of New York, Department of Traffic Annual Report, 1962 (see Box 3, Folder 4).
    - [Far Rockaway No. 1 Field], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
      A view of Far Rockaway No. 1 Field, at Beach 22nd Street and Mott Avenue, Queens, under the elevated railroad trestle.
    - [Far Rockaway No. 2 Field], [1962] (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
      A view of Far Rockaway No. 2 Field, at Beach 21st and 22nd Streets at Mott Avenue, Queens. Published in the City of New York, Department of Traffic Annual Report, 1962 (see Box 3, Folder 4).
    - [Flushing No. 1 Field], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
      Views of Flushing No. 1 Field (and later parking deck), on the block bounded by 39th Avenue, Union Street, 37th Avenue, and 138th Street, at different stages. The photographs capture the lost Macedonia A.M.E. Church at 37-22 Union Street (demolished c. 2018-2019), which was surrounded by the parking lot.
    - [Forest Hills], 1966 March 2 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
      Original folder labeled "Forest Hills Site, 71 Rd. Queens - Pictures." Contains views of 71st Road and vicinity, near the Forest Hills station on the Long Island Rail Road.
    - [Hillside Avenue & Midland Parkway], 1971 July 15 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
      Original folder labeled "Hillside & Midland Parkway, Pictures." Contains views of a parking field at Hillside Avenue and Avon Street, Queens.
    - [Jamaica No. 1 Field?], undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
      Views possibly of Jamaica No. 1 Field, on Liberty Avenue between Union Hall Street and New York Boulevard (renamed Guy R. Brewer Boulevard in 1982), Queens. The site is now occupied by York College's Health and Physical Education Building.